var questions     = [

  {
    question: "What happens to the pressure when I increase the number of particles?",
    answers: ["increases","decreases","stays the same"],
    correct: 2
  },

  {
    question: "What happens to the pressure when I increase the volume?",
    answers: ["increases","decreases","stays the same"],
    correct: 2
  },

  {
    question: "What happens to the pressure when I increase the temperature (i.e., make the particles move faster)?",
    answers: ["increases","decreases","stays the same"],
    correct: 1
  },

  {
    question: "What does the sky look like to an astronaut standing on the Moon?",
    answers: ["Blue just like the sky on Earth.","Gray because of the clouds.","Black because of the clouds.","Black because there is no scattering of light."],
    correct: 4
  },

  {
    question: "Which of the following best describes the greenhouse effect?",
    answers: ["Heat from the interior of the Earth is trapped by the Earth's atmosphere.","Heat from the interior of the Earth only leaks into space very slowly.","Energy from solar radiation is trapped by rocks on Earth's surface.","Energy from solar radiation is trapped by the Earth's atmosphere."],
    correct: 4
  },

  {
    question: "Which of the following fictional planets would you expect to have the highest albedo?",
    answers: ["Coruscant, which is covered by streets and buildings.","Dagobah, which is covered by a jungle.","Hoth, which is covered by snow and ice.","Naboo, which is covered by swamps and grassy plains."],
    correct: 3
  },

  {
    question: "Suppose two rocky planets, Alpha and Beta are identical except that Alpha's air is clear while Beta is covered by clouds.  Which planet would you expect to have a higher surface temperature, and why?",
    answers: ["Alpha will have a higher surface temperature because it absorbs more light from its star.","Alpha will have a higher surface temperature because it reflects more light from its star.","Beta will have a higher surface temperature because it absorbs more light from its star.","Beta will have a higher surface temperature because it reflects more light from its star."],
    correct: 1
  },

  {
    question: "Evidence that Mars used to have liquid water implies that the early Martian atmosphere was",
    answers: ["thicker and warmer than today.","thinner and colder than today.","composed mostly of methane and ammonia.","composed mostly of nitrogen and oxygen."],
    correct: 1
  },

  {
    question: "Most of the CO_2 outgassed from Earth's interior",
    answers: ["was destroyed by solar radiation.","was incorporated into rocks.","is found in today's atmosphere.","is found in today's oceans."],
    correct: 2
  },

  {
    question: "Most of the CO_2 outgassed from Venus's interior",
    answers: ["was destroyed by solar radiation.","was incorporated into rocks.","is found in today's atmosphere.","is found in today's oceans."],
    correct: 3
  },

  {
    question: "There are four geological processes that directly affect planetary surfaces.  Which of the following is not one?",
    answers: ["erosion","volcanism","impact cratering","differentiation"],
    correct: 4
  },

  {
    question: "Why does Earth have many fewer craters than the Moon?",
    answers: ["Earth has had many fewer impacts than the Moon.","Earth formed later than the Moon.","Earth's surface changes more frequently than the Moon's.","Earth has a greenhouse effect while the Moon does not."],
    correct: 3
  },

  {
    question: "Why is the material in terrestrial planets separated into metallic cores and rocky lithospheres?",
    answers: ["In the protoplanetary disk, metal cores formed first and then accreted rocky crusts.","In the hot interior, metals have been created by radioactive decay.","In the hot interior, chemical reactions have transformed rock into metal.","When the planets were molten, metals sank and rocks floated."],
    correct: 4
  },

  {
    question: "Which of the following is not a process that supplies heat to a planet?",
    answers: ["radioactivity","differentiation","impacts","convection"],
    correct: 4
  },

  {
    question: "Which of the following is not a correct statement of ideas from the theory of plate tectonics?",
    answers: ["Plates are destroyed at subduction zones.","All volcanic activity occurs at subduction zones.","Plates are created at mid-ocean ridges.","Earth's crust is broken into plates."],
    correct: 2
  },

  {
    question: "We generally expect the terrestrial planet with the least geological activity today to be the",
    answers: ["oldest","largest","smallest","most dense"],
    correct: 3
  },

  {
    question: "When examining a picture of the lunar surface, you notice that material ejected from the crater Stebbins partly fills in the crater Birkhoff.  You conclude that",
    answers: ["Stebbins was created by an impact, while Birkhoff was created by a volcanic eruption.","Stebbins was created by a volcanic eruption, while Birkhoff was created by an impact.","Stebbins formed before Birkhoff.","Stebbins formed after Birkhoff."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Astronaut footprints on the Moon will probably",
    answers: ["exist for >10,000 years because there is very little weathering on the Moon.","exist for >10,000 years because the Moon's surface is extremely hard and durable.","be eliminated in <10,000 years by erosion. ","None of the above; the footprints are already gone."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Which statement about Mercury's scarps is correct?",
    answers: ["They are similar to clifflike features seen on other terrestrial planets.","They mark the edges of very large craters.","They mark the boundaries of plates in Mercury's lithosphere.","They are a related to the fact that Mercury's core is very large relative to the planet's overall size."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Why isn't Mercury still geologically active?",
    answers: ["It is too close to the Sun, so its surface is too hot.","It is too close to the Sun, so its interior is too hot.","It is too small, so its internal heat has been lost.","It did not include any radioactive material when it formed, so it never had a source of internal heat."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "Craters are rarer on the surface of Venus than on the surfaces of Mercury and the Moon because",
    answers: ["Venus is farther from the asteroid belt and thus has fewer impacts.","the surface of Venus is too hard to be affected by impacts.","running water has erased nearly all of the craters on Venus.","Venus has a thicker atmosphere and has experienced more 'recent' volcanic eruptions."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Suppose a planet has many different surface features such as large valleys, smooth plains, and mountains that show signs of erosion. What can you say about the following statements based on this information? (i) The planet has had recent geological activity. (ii) The planet has an atmosphere. (iii) The planet has a strong magnetic field. (iv) The planet is in its star's habitable zone.",
    answers: ["i and ii must be correct, but there is not enough information to decide about the others.","i and iii must be correct, but there is not enough information to decide about the others.","i, ii, and iii must be correct, but there is not enough information to decide about iv.","ii and iv must be correct, but there is not enough information to decide about the others."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "How are the Jovian planets affected by their rotation?",
    answers: ["Rapid rotation flings heavy elements to the surface while hydrogen and helium remain in the core.","Rapid rotation make the planets slightly stretched (larger pole-to-pole than across the equator), with many cloud bands.","Rapid rotation make the planets slightly stretched (larger pole-to-pole than across the equator), with few cloud bands.","Rapid rotation make the planets slightly flattened (larger across the equator than pole-to-pole), with many cloud bands."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "The Jovian planets are made mainly of which two elements?",
    answers: ["hydrogen and helium","oxygen and nitrogen","carbon and silicon","iron and nickel"],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Why are methane clouds not seen on Jupiter and Saturn?",
    answers: ["Jupiter and Saturn do not have enough methane to make clouds.","Because of their relatively warmer temperatures, Jupiter and Saturn have clouds of water that obscure our view of their methane clouds.","The atmospheres of Jupiter and Saturn are too warm for methane clouds to form.","Jupiter and Saturn have sulfur compounds that combine with all their methane to make reddish methane-sulfide clouds."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "The Coriolis effect causes deflections to the right in the northern hemisphere, and to the left in the southern hemisphere.  Near the equator, convection causes air near Earth surface to flow toward the equator.  What does that imply for the direction of prevailing winds on the north and south sides of the equator? north of the equator / south of the equator",
    answers: ["east / east","east / west","west / east","west / west"],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Venus rotates much slower than Earth.  How do the Coriolis effect and number of atmospheric bands on Venus compare to Earth?",
    answers: ["stronger / more","stronger / fewer","weaker / more","weaker / fewer"],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Jupiter's cold cloud-top temperature helps the planet retain hydrogen in its atmosphere because",
    answers: ["cold atoms and molecules move more slowly.","cold atoms and molecules move more quickly.","cold atoms and molecules are heavier.","cold atoms and molecules are lighter"],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "The source of energy for Io's volcanoes is",
    answers: ["thermal radiation from Jupiter. ","heat left over from its formation.","radioactive decay inside Io. ","tidal heating from Jupiter. "],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "What is the correct chain of cause and effect for the tidal heating of Io, Europa, and Ganymede?",
    answers: ["Tidal forces preserve elliptical orbits, which result in a gravitational resonance.","Elliptical orbits cause tidal heating, which results in a gravitational resonance.","Tidal forces cause a gravitational resonance, which preserves elliptical orbits.","A gravitational resonance preserves elliptical orbits, which result in tidal heating."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Why does tap water transmit electrical current more effectively than pure (distilled) water? ",
    answers: ["The tap water is hotter than the distilled water, so its molecules move around faster.","The tap water is colder than the distilled water, so its molecules move around slower.","The tap water is less dense than the distilled water, so electrical current flows more easily.","The tap water contains charged particles that can carry an electrical current."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following experiments would not create a long-lasting electrical current?",
    answers: ["You place a loop of wire at the exact location of the Earth's south magnetic pole.","You spin a bar magnet at the center of a stationary loop of wire.","You move a bar magnet back and forth through a stationary loop of wire.","You move a loop of wire back and forth around a stationary bar magnet."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Why does a magnet dropped inside the copper tube fall more slowly than a magnet dropped outside the copper tube? ",
    answers: ["The magnet falling inside the tube experiences friction from the sides of the tube.","The magnet falling inside the tube experiences more air resistance.","The magnet falling inside the tube causes electrical currents to flow in the tube, which generate an opposing magnetic field.","The tube causes electrical currents to flow inside the magnet, which generate an opposing magnetic field."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "Saturn's rings are",
    answers: ["solid enough to stand on.","a collection of solid particles.","a collection of liquid drops.","thin streams of gas."],
    correct: 2
  },
  {
    question: "After Saturn's rings were discovered, people wondered whether the rings were solid or made of many particles orbiting independently.  Is there a difference between the rotational motion of solid rings and that of particle rings?",
    answers: ["No.  In both cases, the outer edge moves slower than the inner edge.","No.  In both cases, the outer edge moves faster than the inner edge.","Yes.  Solid ring: outer edge moves slower than inner edge.  Particle ring: outer edge moves faster than inner edge.","Yes.  Solid ring: outer edge moves faster than inner edge.  Particle ring: outer edge moves slower than inner edge."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Why don't ring particles form a moon?",
    answers: ["Their masses are too small for them to accrete.","They collide too infrequently to make a moon.","Tidal forces from moons prevent them from accreting.","Tidal forces from the planet prevent them from accreting."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Saturn occasionally 'occults,' or passes in front of, a distant star. What happens when the rings pass in front of the star?",
    answers: ["The star brightens because its light is focused by the rings.","The star disappears completely and does not reappear until Saturn moves out of the way.","The star 'flickers,' disappearing and reappearing as different ring structures cross the star.","The star changes color because the light is affected by the rings' motion through the Doppler effect."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "What time of day was today's Astronomy Picture of the Day taken?",
    answers: ["morning","midday","evening"],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following features provides the best evidence that Pluto remains geologically active?",
    answers: ["Cthulu Regio","Viking Terra","Hayabusa Terra","Sputnik Planum"],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Mt. Everest on Earth is 8848 m tall.  Olympus Mons on Mars is 21,230 m tall.  The Hillary Montes on Pluto are about 3500 m tall.  Put them in order from smallest to largest *relative* to the planet. NOTE: Earth 6371 km, Mars 3390 km, Pluto 1187 km",
    answers: ["Mt. Everest, Hillary Montes, Olympus Mons","Mt. Everest, Olympus Mons, Hillary Montes","Hillary Montes, Mt. Everest, Olympus Mons","Hillary Montes, Olympus Mons, Mt. Everest"],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "When we observe a distant planet (or dwarf planet) with an optical telescope, what are we actually seeing?",
    answers: ["Reflected light from the Sun.","Thermal emission from the planet itself.","Emission lines from the planet's atmosphere.","Glow from the planet's volcanoes."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following affect(s) the reflected brightness of a planet?",
    answers: ["albedo","distance from Sun","size","all three: size, distance from Sun, and albedo"],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "What is the best way to determine the albedo of an object that appears only as a dot in our best telescopes?",
    answers: ["Assume a typical albedo for similar types of objects.","Make a guess based on the object's density.","Compare the object's reflected and emitted brightnesses.","Use the Doppler effect."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "How can we measure both the reflected and emitted brightnesses of a distant, cold object?",
    answers: ["Use an optical telescope.","Use an infrared telescope.","Use an ultraviolet telescope.","Use both optical and infrared telescopes."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "What is the best way to determine the size of a distant object that appears only as a dot in our best telescopes?  (Assume we know the distance to the object.)",
    answers: ["Hope that a stellar occultation event will happen soon.","Measure its brightness in optical light and assume an average albedo.","Measure its brightness in both optical and infrared light.","Measure its mass and assume an average density."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "We have good information about the masses of four of the five largest trans-Neptunian objects.  Which one has the hardest mass to measure, and why?",
    answers: ["Eris because it has the most eccentric orbit.","Quaoar because it has the least eccentric orbit.","Makemake because it does not have a moon.","Pluto because its five moons get in the way."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "Plutinos are trans-Neptunian objects that all have a semimajor axis of 40 AU (just like Pluto), but different eccentricities (some have orbits that are more eccentric than Pluto's, while other are less).  What can you say about their orbital periods?",
    answers: ["All Plutinos have the same orbital period as Pluto.","All Plutinos have orbital periods shorter than Pluto's.","All Plutinos have orbital periods longer than Pluto's.","There are periods both longer and shorter than Pluto's."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Most of the planets we have seen so far are Jovian planets far from their stars. Should we conclude that there are few warm terrestrial planets in the Milky Way?",
    answers: ["No, because the observations are probably wrong.","No, because the  observations are probably biased.","Yes, because that is what the observational evidence says."],
    correct: 2
  },
  {
    question: "Most of you are Yankees or Mets fans. Should we conclude that there are few Twins fans in the U.S.?",
    answers: ["No, because the observations are probably wrong.","No, because the  observations are probably biased.","Yes, because that is what the observational evidence says.","Yes, because who would want to root for the Twins?!"],
    correct: 2
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the center of mass of a donut located?",
    answers: ["Somewhere on the inner edge of the donut.","Somewhere on the outer edge of the donut.","In the middle of the hole of the donut.","A donut doesn't have a center of mass."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "The orbital period of an unseen planet",
    answers: ["is the same as the period of the star's Doppler curve.","is shorter than the star's period.","is longer than the star's period.","might be longer or shorter than the star's period, depending on the orbit's eccentricity."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Jupiter is about 1/10 the diameter (or radius) of the Sun.  If Jupiter transited the Sun, by about how much would the Sun's light dim?",
    answers: ["0.1% (the Sun would be about 99.9% of its regular brightness)","1% (the Sun would be about 99% of its regular brightness)","10% (the Sun would be 90% of its regular brightness)","30% (the Sun would be about 70% of its regular brightness)"],
    correct: 2
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following changes cannot be used to infer the presence of a planet in orbit around a star?",
    answers: ["A change in the star's position.","A change in the star's line-of-sight velocity.","A change in the star's color.","A change in the star's own brightness."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "In what way(s) is the Doppler method biased?",
    answers: ["toward massive over low-mass planets","toward close over far planets","toward large over small planets","both A and B"],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "In what way(s) is the transit method biased?",
    answers: ["toward massive over low-mass planets","toward close over far planets","toward large over small planets","both B and C"],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Suppose we observe that a particular star with the same mass as the Sun has a *small* Doppler wobble. What can we say about the properties of the planet causing the wobble?",
    answers: ["We can deduce the planet's distance from the star, and we can be certain the planet has a low mass.","We can deduce the planet's distance from the star, and we can be certain the orbit is nearly face-on.","We can deduce the planet's distance from the star, but we cannot say whether the planet has a low mass or a nearly face-on orbit.","We cannot say anything for sure without more information."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following statements about the Doppler method and the transit method is correct?",
    answers: ["If we detect an exoplanet with the transit method, our viewing angle is favorable for detecting it with the Doppler method, too.","If we can detect a planet with the Doppler method, it should also be detectable with the transit method.","Both the Doppler method and the transit method can tell us the size of an exoplanet.","Neither the Doppler method nor the transit method can tell us the size of an exoplanet."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "In order to learn about the composition of a distant planet, the two most important properties to determine are the planet's",
    answers: ["mass and size.","mass and orbital period.","size and orbital period.","orbital period and eccentricity."],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Here are velocity curves for two similar stars with exoplanets.  What can you deduce about the shapes of the planets' orbits?",
    answers: ["Both Alderaan and Bespin have circular orbits.","Both Alderaan and Bespin have very elongated orbits.","Alderaan's orbit is circular, while Bespin's orbit is very elongated.","Alderaan's orbit is very elongated, while Bespin's orbit is circular."],
    correct: 3
  },
  {
    question: "Here is a transit light curve for a star with two planets.  What can you deduce from this figure about the planets?",
    answers: ["The smaller planet is closer to the star.","The smaller planet is farther from the star.","The smaller planet is denser.","The two planets are the same distance from the star but different sizes."],
    correct: 2
  },
  {
    question: "Suppose you have a time machine with a dial that you can spin to send you to any time in Earth's history. If you spin the dial and travel to a random time, what is most likely to happen to you?",
    answers: ["You will be eaten by dinosaurs.","You will be mauled by a saber tooth tiger.","You will be killed by a cataclysmic event (e.g., a volcanic eruption of an asteroid impact).","You will suffocate because you won't be able to breathe the air."],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is not a basic requirement for life (as we know it)?",
    answers: ["a source of light","a source of nutrients","a source of energy","liquid water"],
    correct: 1
  },
  {
    question: "Astronomers typically draw the habitable zone as though it depends only on the star, but strictly speaking it depends on some planet properties as well. Which of the following are the most important properties for determining whether a planet has the right temperature to support life (as we know it)?",
    answers: ["mass and number of craters","size and number of moons","density and rotation period","albedo and atmospheric characteristics"],
    correct: 4
  },
  {
    question: "Which chemical signature in the spectrum of light from a planet would best indicate life?",
    answers: ["carbon dioxide","water","sulfuric acid","oxygen"],
    correct: 4
  }

];
